Guide to the J. S. Johnston Photographs circa 1890-1899 PR 219
New-York Historical Society
J. S. Johnston photographs
circa 1890-1899
New-York Historical Society
Johnston, J. S. (John S.), approximately 1839-1899
PR 219
2.75 Linear feet in 5 boxes. 76 b&w glass negatives (8 x 10 in.); 6 b&w glass negatives (5 x 8 in.); 8 gelatin silver prints (11 x 14 in.).
Collection of photographs taken circa 1890-1899 by J.S Johnston, including original glass negatives and modern gelatin silver photographic prints. The photographs are pleasant pictorial depictions of New York City landmarks such as the Brooklyn Bridge, Union Square, and Castle Garden, as well as of Niagara Falls, Boston landmarks, the Hudson River valley, Puerto Rico, Montreal, and Quebec. There are also some images of shipping, and of Buffalo Bill (William F. Cody) and his Wild West show. All negatives and photographs bear Johnston's handwritten captions and numbers, and most are dated. Photographic prints in this collection were printed in the 1960s and 1970s from oversize vintage glass negatives that were later destroyed. Online version.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was removed from the Negative File (PR-045) and the George P. Hall & Son Photograph Collection (PR-024) in 2003.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in two series based on format. Items within each series are arranged by Johnston's negative numbers.
Series I.
Negatives, circa 1890-1899
Series II.
Photographic Prints, circa 1892-1895
Biographical / Historical
John S. Johnston (circa 1839–1899) was a late 19th-century maritime and landscape photographer best known for his images of yachts and New York City landmarks. His work appeared in 1890s periodicals that featured boat racing, such as Outing Magazine, and Forest and Stream (later absorbed by Field & Stream).
For the scant known details of Johnston's life, see his obituary in the New York Times: "Dies Trying to Hide Identity," December 19, 1899.
Related Materials
Additional views by J. S. Johnston at the New-York Historical Society are found in the Stereograph Collection (PR-065), the Geographic Images Collection, and in the Negative File (PR-045).
Scope and Contents
The bulk of J. S. Johnston's images in this collection show popular sites in Manhattan at the end of the 19th-century, including churches (Trinity Church, St. Patrick's Cathedral, and the Church of the Transfiguration, affectionately called the "Little Church Around the Corner"), bridges (Brooklyn Bridge, Washington Bridge), statuary (Christopher Columbus in Central Park, Nathan Hale in City Hall Park), parks (Central Park and Union Square), and early skyscrapers (St. Paul Building, Manhattan Life Building). Views farther afield were taken at Niagara Falls, and in Massachusetts (Longfellow's House at Cambridge, and the Old South Church, King's Chapel, and Old State House in Boston), Montreal, Quebec (city and province), and Puerto Rico.
The complete collection of J. S. Johnston photographs has been digitized and may be viewed online through the New-York Historical Society's Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
Glass negatives.; Wet collodion negatives.; Gelatin silver prints.; Photographic prints.; Shipping -- New York (State) -- New York.; Boston (Mass.) -- Photographs.; New York (N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Brooklyn Bridge (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Union Square (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs; Hudson River (N.Y. and N.J.) -- Photographs; Niagara Falls (N.Y. and Ont.) -- Photographs.; Puerto Rico -- Photographs; Montréal (Québec) -- Photographs; Québec (Québec) -- Photographs; Buffalo Bill, 1846-1917 -- Portraits; Buffalo Bill's Wild West Show -- Photographs; Castle Garden (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs
- Series I. Negatives, circa 1890-1899
  Arrangement
  Negatives are filed by Johnston's handwritten numbers. Descriptions are the photographer's. Unless noted otherwise, all negatives measure 8 x 10 inches.
  - St. Paul Building, N.Y. [negative 7], 1897 (Box 1)
  - New York Bay from Brooklyn Bridge [negative 13], undated (Box 1)
  - Castle Garden & Bay, N.Y. [negative 16], undated (Box 1)
  - Manhattan Club, N.Y. (Residence of A.T. Stewart) [negative 38], 1899 (Box 1)
  - Brooklyn Bridge, N.Y. (4 views) [negatives 52-60], 1897, undated (Box 1)
  - The Waldorf Astoria [negative 63A], 1898 (Box 1)
  - Union Trust Co. Building & Trinity Churchyard, N.Y. [negative 72 (copy negative)], undated (Box 1)
  - Washington Bridge, N.Y. [negative 117], 1893 April (Box 1)
  - Elephants in Central Park [negative 147], undated (Box 1)
  - Statue of Columbus, Central Park, N.Y. [negative 165A], 1895 February (Box 1)
  - Broadway, N.Y. [negative 202], 1895 (Box 1)
  - Castle Williams, Governor's Island, N.Y. [negative 206], undated (Box 1)
  - Printing House Square, N.Y. [negative 217], circa 1890-1899 (Box 1)
  - New Armory 22nd Regiment N.G.S., N.Y. [negative 230], [undated?] (Box 1)
  - Washington Bridge, 181st St., N.Y. [negative 233], undated (Box 1)
  - Wall Street, N.Y. [negative 244], undated (Box 1)
  - St. Patrick's Cathedral - Pulpit [negative 271 (copy negative)], undated (Box 1)
  - Interior, Trinity Church, N.Y. [negative 273], undated (Box 1)
  - Statue of Nathan Hale, N.Y. (City Hall Park) [negative 288], 1894 (Box 1)
  - Longfellow's House, Cambridge, Mass. [negative 423], undated (Box 2)
  - Old South Church, Boston [negative 431], undated (Box 2)
  - King's Chapel, Boston [negative 434], undated (Box 2)
  - Old State House, Boston [negative 435], undated (Box 2)
  - Hudson River (7 views) [negatives 509-540], 1894-1899, undated (Box 2)
  - Niagara Falls (11 views) [negatives 605-638], 1894, undated (Box 2)
  - Niagara Falls (cont.) (14 views) [negatives 640-682], 1892, undated (Box 3)
  - S.S. Kaiser Wilhelm Der Grosse [negative 795], 1897 (Box 3)
  - U.S. Rev. Cutter Grant [negative 800], undated (Box 3)
  - New Orleans, U.S.N. (at Navy Yard, N.Y.) [negative 809], 1898 April 20 (Box 3)
  - Castine, U.S.N. [negative 886], undated (Box 3)
  - Rockaway Beach [negative 930], undated (Box 3)
  - Gulls, N.Y. Bay [negative 996], 1897 (Box 3)
  - Montreal, Canada (9 views) [negatives 1002-1020], 1897, undated (Box 3)
  - Quebec, Canada (city and province) (11 views) [negatives 1030-1108], undated (Box 4)
  - Buffalo Bill's Wild West Show (6 views) [negatives 1115-1123], circa 1892 (Box 4)
  - Viking Ship [negative 1249], undated (Box 4)
  - Ojo de Agua, Aquadilla, Puerto Rico (5 x 8 in.) [negative 1311], undated (Box 4)
  - Mayaquez [Mayagüez], Puerto Rico (5 views) (5 x 8 in.) [negatives 1313-1319], undated (Box 4)
- Series II. Photographic Prints, circa 1892-1895
  Photographic prints are filed by Johnston's negative numbers. Dates reflect when the photographs were taken. The prints (with the exception of number 208, which is vintage) were made from oversize vintage glass negatives in the 1960s and 1970s as part of a reformatting project. The negatives were subsequently destroyed.
  - Madison Square Garden, N.Y. [from negative 64A], 1893 (Box 5)
  - Little Church Around the Corner [from negative 208], circa 1892 (Box 5)
  - El. R.R. Curve, 110th St. N.Y. [from negative 3000], 1894 (Box 5)
  - Broadway, N.Y. [from negative 3002], 1894 (Box 5)
  - Union Square, N.Y. [from negative 3003], 1894 (Box 5)
  - Terrace & Lake, Central Park, N.Y. [from negative 3015], 1894 (Box 5)
  - View up East River N.Y. [from negative 3028], 1894 (Box 5)
  - Hotel Netherland, N.Y. (59th St. Entrance to Central Park) (Millionaire's Club) (Hotel Savoy) [from negative 3029], 1894 (Box 5)
  - Manhattan Life Building, N.Y. (Trinity Church) (Surety Building) (Union Trust Co. Building) (Consolidated Exchange Building) [from negative 3036], 1895 (Box 5)